here we
go Fridays Fridays we love our Fridays
don't we we love them we are doing all
kinds of different things on a Friday
TGIF
right look it up if you don't know what
it means Fridays are when a lot of
companies give learning time away and
we're going to talk about what that
means and why you should insist upon it
but the short answer if you don't have
to watch anything else in the video is
when you're deciding where to work one
of the points of data points that you
should research is do they provide time
on the job to learn if they don't now no
companies on the planet these days
provide money to go to training and by
the way they shouldn't that's a totally
stupid thing and I may talk about that
at the end of the video so hang on to
your you know to the rest of the video
go to the end or something about why I
think paying for training is totally
idiotic and stupid especially
conferences might have its own video I
don't know we'll see um but the idea
that a company that you work for should
give you particularly a technology
company should give you time to learn
and to work on your own projects related
to what's required at work or not is now
table Stakes as they say it's a poker
term I don't know where it comes from
that is if if you if you don't have that
you should literally walk the other way
because every other tech company pretty
much offers that if if you are not you
shouldn't probably start with that
question hey am I going to get Friday's
off so I can learn that should probably
be not how much vacation am I get I mean
you need to show interest obviously in
the in the employer You're Building
trust with them but one way that they
can demonstrate trust in you is that
they can give you the time on Friday
some companies is it happen day some
companies it's a whole day they all have
a different name for it when I was at
IBM it was think Friday um you know
every company has got a different name
for that that time and and by the way be
careful they will try to take it from
you right so they will try to to have
organized training during that time
because it's supposed to be for training
and then and then your manager say oh
they just gave us Fridays for my team to
learn what I want them to learn that is
not how it works my friends that is not
how it works it is supposed to be
unfettered Guiltless learning and work
on your own projects and by the way this
is this is how Gmail was invented this
is how Google Maps was invented some of
the biggest projects ever invented in
Silicon Valley or elsewhere have come
about as people's passion projects where
they autodidactic learned everything
they needed to make a thing that didn't
exist and they were they look forward to
their Fridays because they could use
that Friday instead of you know getting
drunk at 5:00 or something they would
you know be burning the midnight oil or
whatever working on their favorite
project that they started that their
company was smart enough to say you can
work on this so whether or not you're
getting that time to do your own
learning uh or you're getting that time
to work your own projects in my opinion
they're kind of
similar and thankfully the company that
I work for does uh very clearly and
cleanly give us that time uh to to work
on things and I regularly stream that uh
the things that I'm learning on my own
like right now I'm I'm really diving
deep into GitHub uh actions and so
that's the thing that's the thing that
we're doing right now we're making a
video right now so happy happy to talk
to you in a second um so that is it make
sure that you're doing that and there's
something that kind of goes along with
this right so most tech companies are
going to require that you commit to
learning on your own time I started by
talking about how you know you should
expect a company to give you that time
but this video has got two major points
to it the first one is yes the company
should be giving you enough time uh and
that should be paid time by the way uh
to learn should they send you off to
training and conferences no maybe
another video for that um but the other
piece of this is that the company people
that are hiring you they are trusting
you and the if you're going to join the
it Lifestyle the company the employer I
don't know if this is purely an it we
could have a conversation about that but
I think that absolutely in it one of the
points the expectations one of the
points of trust with this employer or
employee relationship is that you will
learn what is necessary to do the job
can he get the job yes I'm not arguing
with that can he do the job I'm not
arguing that with you I know he can get
the job but can he do the job I'm not
arguing with that with you if you can't
do the job because you don't know
the employer expects you to figure it
out and they don't have to tell you that
that is a bottom line expectation and if
you are not okay being expected to learn
on your own time in addition to the
Friday that they give you and that means
I mean not all of the education that
you're going to need is going to fit
into even eight hours on a Friday
sometimes if I mean like when you get
thrown into kubernetes you know if
you're a salaried employee you're the
number of hours doesn't even matter
anymore right it's it just means that
you've got to make the time and if if
you have a deadline and the company's
established a deadline and you don't
know the thing and you're being
responsible to do the thing then you're
expected to learn it and that and you
need to be okay with that if you are not
okay not knowing things uh then this is
not the lifestyle for you because you
are going to have to learn constantly
and you need to set up a plan about the
next thing you need to learn is
important you need to be able to
prioritize the things that you feel are
the most important for you to learn and
that does doesn't just go for your
current employer that goes for your
career that that the really great the
really important part about making
Fridays anything you want to
learn is that you can maintain your
career trajectory you may be in a job
doing web development but you want to
learn go so you can do backend or
middleware
development and your employer or whoever
and and you you need to set forth your
own plan there's another video about
becoming an autodidact and what that
means and that is it
what are the Technologies I need to
learn to advance my career path whatever
it is and you need to decide and there's
lots of videos I've made already about
establishing what it is you want to do
and where you want to go but so you may
not want to be a desktop support person
your whole life right but it might you
you took the A+ exam and now you're a
desktop support person you're getting
paid Tech money instead of you know
waiter money um but now you want to do
more I want to become a network engineer
but it's not a part of your immediate
job well a good company is going to give
you Fridays to learn that stuff I'm like
why are you learning network engineering
they should never ask that question and
if they do go work someplace else I'm
telling you and I mean if you want to
accept that that's up to you obviously
but you need to not forget the fact that
you need to put on your list the things
that you need to learn next right and
sometimes that might let some of your
skills like kind of fade you can't be
focusing on all your skills at all the
same time there's another video about
Focus um you can't just it's impossible
especially in Tech you need to be able
to look things up and do the research
really quickly I call it just in time
learning that probably deserves this own
its own video but just in time learning
is developing research skills and
note-taking skills and and being able to
query the internet as fast as possible
and there's going to be lots of videos
about to do that like for example how to
do text based web searching in a
fraction of the time in literally
seconds where it would have taken you a
minute or two using a graphic interface
we're going to do that in the Boost uh
there's other videos about how to use
text based browsing how to use chat GPT
from the command line how to back it up
with an actual internet search and then
how to how to query your own zcas and
database your own knowledge base of
accumulated notes and have that be your
way to get an answer quickly to a
problem it's more important that you're
able to learn quickly and able to look
up what you learned particularly as you
age like me because my memory is not
what it was and I've got to be able to
look all those things up so this has
kind of been a into a lot of other
videos that we're going to do uh
regarding you know just in time learning
in particular and specific techniques
about how to do that but the when you
sign up for a tech job you are signing
up with the expectation that number one
you are going to learn what's necessary
to do the job and and two that your
employer is going to give you the time
to learn that job and then I'm going to
end on something that's rather negative
but I'm going to say it anyway your
employer doesn't owe you training
period they don't owe you anything in
2024 this whole you know organizational
man you're going to get a watch when you
retire stuff it's all gone this is an
atwi employment thing that means you can
leave anytime and as long as you keep
your toolbox full of sharpened tools you
can leave anytime it's another reason
for you to make sure that you're
learning what you want in your career
because you are in control of your
career you can leave anytime and if
there's one
empowering the empowering nature of
learning skills an it is extremely
valuable because you can leave anytime
and go someplace else in fact you'll
have recruiters knocking on your door I
I I I'm thinking of Greg Greg you out
there I'm thinking of Greg Greg has got
people regularly coming to them to them
uh saying hey I got another job over
here for you because they know how good
the reputation is so good he you know
he's been keeping his own skills up and
he's been doing it your your company
doesn't owe you anything but time to do
the learning necessary to do the job and
for you to keep your own career
progressed they do not owe you a trip
they do not owe you money for a
conference and I've already told you the
story about about the time I got sent to
training just to repeat it really
quickly for the sake of time um I was
sent I was sent to some training it cost
2,300 bucks or so and the other guy we
all got the same certificate and I put
the extra time in I actually used my off
time and they just got drunk and didn't
do anything and they didn't learn
anything and then they came and then I I
negotiated with with my I just I'm
repeating this I'm sorry if you've
already heard it just stop now so I told
my manager when I got back I said hey I
don't want to do that I said I give give
me half the money I'll buy books and
I'll do it and I did this story as a
method of backing up yourself because I
know I've got those books available that
I can go to and that was a way to to
squelch my impostor syndrome because I
know I can answer any question I wanted
to so there is another video on impostor
syndrome where I talk about the story
but the point is that by you know my
manager did if there is a budget at all
you use that budget to spend it on
resources but it's the most important
thing you can get from your employer is
time time for you to work on learning
those things and secondarily perhaps
money uh to buy books but as you know
the internet you can learn anything
without a book I mean some of the books
are a little bit better some some
companies already have those books but
if you're going to get money negotiate
to have that money go towards resources
and not toward especially conferences
there are waste of time conferences are
an extremely huge waste of time I'll
make a whole video about that um you
don't learn anything from them you
you're out money they are they you get
drunk you have run with your friends you
get to meet your Heroes great they're
not educational I mean the amount of
Education that you can get from a
conference per minute and per dollar is
ridiculous compared to what you could do
on your own time if you were just given
the same amount of time on a Friday to
do that not to mention the fact you
could watch all the Salient points of
the conference by yourself and glean out
that information stop lying and telling
people you need to go to a conference
because because of the training all
right I'm done enough complaining for me